<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="instance-management">
  <title>Instance security management</title>

  <para>
    One of the virtues of running instances in a virtualized environment
    is that it opens up new opportunities for security controls that are
    not typically available when deploying onto bare metal. There are
    several technologies that can be applied to the virtualization stack
    that bring improved information assurance for cloud tenants.
  </para>
  <para>
    Deployers or users of OpenStack with strong security requirements
    may want to consider deploying these technologies. Not all are
    applicable in every situation, indeed in some cases technologies may
    be ruled out for use in a cloud because of prescriptive business
    requirements. Similarly some technologies inspect instance data such
    as run state which may be undesirable to the users of the system.
  </para>
  <para>
    In this chapter we explore these technologies and describe the
    situations where they can be used to enhance security for instances
    or underlying instances. We also seek to highlight where privacy
    concerns may exist. These include data pass through, introspection,
    or providing a source of entropy. In this section we highlight the
    following additional security services:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist><listitem>
      <para>
        Entropy to instances
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Scheduling instances to nodes
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Trusted images
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Instance migrations
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Monitoring, alerting, and reporting
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Updates and patches
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Firewalls and other host-based security controls
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <xi:include href="section_security-services-for-instances.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="section_case-studies-instance-management.xml"/>

</chapter>
