<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="dashboard-domain-names">
      <title>Domain names</title>
      <para>Many organizations typically deploy web applications at
        subdomains of an overarching organization domain. It is natural
        for users to expect a domain of the form
          <uri>openstack.example.org</uri>. In this context, there are
        often applications which are deployed in the same second-level
        namespace. This name structure is convenient and simplifies name
        server maintenance.</para>
      <para>We strongly recommend deploying dashboard to a
        <emphasis>second-level domain</emphasis>, such as
        <uri>https://example.com</uri>, rather than deploying
        dashboard on a <emphasis>shared subdomain</emphasis> of any level,
        for example <uri>https://openstack.example.org</uri> or
        <uri>https://horizon.openstack.example.org</uri>. We also
        advise against deploying to bare internal domains like
        <uri>https://horizon/</uri>. These recommendations are based on the
        limitations of browser same-origin-policy.</para>
      <para>Recommendations given in this guide cannot effectively guard against
        known attacks if you deploy the dashboard in a domain that also hosts
        user-generated content, even when this content resides on a separate
        sub-domain. User-generated content can consist of scripts, images, or uploads
        of any type. Most major web presences, including googleusercontent.com,
        fbcdn.com, github.io, and twimg.co, use this approach to segregate
        user-generated content from cookies and security tokens.</para>
      <para>If you do not follow this recommendation regarding
        second-level domains, avoid a cookie-backed session store and
        employ HTTP Strict Transport Security (HSTS). When deployed on
        a subdomain, the dashboard's security is equivalent to the least secure
        application deployed on the same second-level domain.</para>
</section>
