<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="data-processing-case-studies">
  <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
  <title>Case studies</title>
  <para>
    Continuing with the studies described in
    <xref linkend="introduction-to-case-studies"/>, we present Alice and
    Bob's approaches to deploying the Data processing service for their
    users.
  </para>
  <section xml:id="data-processing-case-studies-alice">
    <title>Alice's private cloud</title>
    <para>
      Alice is deploying the Data processing service for a group of users
      that are trusted members of a collaboration. They are all placed in a
      single project and share the clusters, jobs, and data within. She
      deploys the controller with TLS enabled, using a certificate signed
      by the organization's root certificate. She configures the controller
      to provide floating IP addresses to the cluster instances allowing for
      users to gain access to the instances in the event of errors. She
      enables the use of proxy domains to prevent the users from needing to
      enter their credentials into the Data processing service.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="data-processing-case-studies-bob">
    <title>Bob's public cloud</title>
    <para>
      Bob's public cloud contains users that will not necessarily
      know or trust each other. He puts all users into separate projects.
      Each user has their own clusters, jobs, and data which cannot be
      accessed by other users. He deploys the controller with TLS enabled,
      using a certificate signed by a well known public certificate
      authority. He configures a custom topology to ensure that access to
      the provisioned cluster instances will flow through a controlled
      gateway. He creates a security group that opens only the ports needed
      for the controller to access the frameworks deployed. He enables the
      use of proxy domains to prevent the users from needing to enter their
      credentials into the Data processing service. He configures the
      rootwrap command to allow the data processing controller user to
      run the proxy commands.
    </para>
  </section>
</section>
