<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="case-studies-monitoring-and-logging">
  <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
    <title>Case studies</title>
    <para>In this case study we discuss how Alice and Bob would address monitoring and logging in the public vs a private cloud. In both instances, time synchronization and a centralized store of logs become extremely important for performing proper assessments and troubleshooting of anomalies. Just collecting logs is not very useful, a robust monitoring system must be built to generate actionable events.</para>
    <section xml:id="case-studies-monitoring-and-logging-alice-private-cloud">
      <title>Alice's private cloud</title>
      <para>In the private cloud, Alice has a better understanding of the tenants’ requirements thus she has the ability to add appropriate oversight, actively enforcing compliance for monitoring and logging activities. Alice should identify critical services and data to verify that logging is turned on for each of the services while ensuring the information is being aggregated to a central log server. She should start with simple, known use cases then implement correlation and alerting to limit the number of false positives. To implement correlation and alerting, she sends the log data to her organization's existing SIEM tool. Security monitoring should be an ongoing process therefore she should continue to define use cases and alerts in order to have a better understanding of the network traffic activity and usage over time.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="case-studies-monitoring-and-logging-bob-public-cloud">
      <title>Bob's public cloud</title>
      <para>When it comes to logging, as a public cloud provider, Bob is interested in the activities for situational awareness as well as compliance. In the aspect of compliance, as a provider, Bob is subject to adherence to various rules and regulations to include activities such as providing timely, relevant logs or reports to customers to meet the requirements of their compliance programs. With that in mind, Bob configures all of his instances, nodes, and infrastructure devices to perform time synchronization with an external, validated time device. Additionally, Bob's team has built a Django based web application for his customers to perform self-service log retrieval from the SIEM tool. Bob also uses this SIEM tool along with a robust set of alerts and integration with his CMDB to provide operational awareness to both customers and cloud administrators.</para>
    </section>
</section>
