<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="case-studies-networking">
  <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
    <title>Case studies</title>
    <para>Earlier in <xref linkend="introduction-to-case-studies"/> we introduced
    the Alice and Bob case studies where Alice is deploying a private government
    cloud and Bob is deploying a public cloud each with different
    security requirements. Here we discuss how Alice and Bob would address
    providing networking services to the user.</para>
    <section xml:id="case-studies-networking-alice-private-cloud">
      <title>Alice's private cloud</title>
      <para>Alice picks nova-network due to its stability. She
        understands a migration from nova-network to OpenStack
        Networking (neutron) will not be easy, and keeps a blueprint for
        the migration that is refreshed every OpenStack release. This
        will ensure that Alice and her team are up-to-date with
        OpenStack Networking features even though they are focusing on
        nova-network, and will allow the migration plan to mature with
        Alice's experience with OpenStack to help enable a smooth
        transition.
      </para>
      <para>Alice configures nova-network with the VLAN network manager
        so that each tenant will have its own virtual network, keeping
        in mind the VLAN trunking will stress the environment and the
        scaling limit of 4096 tenants. She is aware that all traffic
        will pass through the virtual networking appliance, however she
        is comfortable with this given the hardware positioned to
        support the VLAN trunking across the entire environment.
        Additionally, as the nova-network hypervisor enforces the
        security group rules with iptables, invalid traffic will not be
        an issue. To ensure this, she designates a quarterly review of
        the security group rules for each VLAN. She understands there is
        no overlapping IP space and has ensured the deployment systems
        have separate IP ranges with room for growth until the migration
        to OpenStack Networking occurs.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="case-studies-networking-bob-public-cloud">
      <title>Bob's public cloud</title>
      <para>A major business driver for Bob is to provide an advanced
      networking services to his customers. Bob's customers would like
      to deploy multi-tiered application stacks. This multi-tiered
      application are either existing enterprise application or newly
      deployed applications. Since Bob's public cloud is a
      multi-tenancy enterprise service, the choice to use for L2
      isolation in this environment is to use overlay
      networking. Another aspect of Bob's cloud is the self-service
      aspect where the customer can provision available networking
      services as needed. These networking services encompass L2
      networks, L3 Routing, Network <glossterm>ACL</glossterm> and
      NAT. It is important that per-tenant quota's be implemented in
      this environment.</para>
      <para>An added benefit with utilizing OpenStack Networking is
      when new advanced networking services become available, these
      new features can be easily provided to the end customers.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
