<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="identity-authentication-methods">
  <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
    <title>Authentication methods</title>

    <section xml:id="identity-authentication-methods-internally-implemented-authentication-methods">
      <title>Internally implemented authentication methods</title>
      <para>The Identity service can store user credentials in an SQL
        Database, or may use an LDAP-compliant directory server. The
        Identity database may be separate from databases used by other
        OpenStack services to reduce the risk of a compromise of the
        stored credentials.</para>
      <para>
        When you use a user name and password to authenticate,
        Identity does not enforce policies on password strength,
        expiration, or failed authentication attempts as recommended
        by NIST Special Publication 800-118 (draft). Organizations
        that desire to enforce stronger password policies should
        consider using Identity extensions or external authentication
        services.</para>
      <para>LDAP simplifies integration of Identity authentication
        into an organization's existing directory service and user
        account management processes.</para>
      <para>Authentication and authorization policy in OpenStack may be
      delegated to another service. A typical use case is an organization
      that seeks to deploy a private cloud and already has a database of employees
      and users in an LDAP system. Using this as the authentication authority,
      requests to the Identity service are delegated to the LDAP system,
      which will then authorize or deny based on its policies. Upon successful authentication,
      the Identity service then generates a token that is used for access to
      authorized services.</para>
      <para>Note that if the LDAP system has attributes defined for
        the user such as admin, finance, HR etc, these must be mapped
        into roles and groups within Identity for use by the various
        OpenStack services. The <filename>/etc/keystone/keystone.conf</filename>
        file maps LDAP attributes to Identity attributes.</para>
      <para>The Identity service <emphasis role="bold">MUST
          NOT</emphasis> be allowed to write to LDAP services used for
        authentication outside of the OpenStack deployment as this
        would allow a sufficiently privileged keystone user to make
        changes to the LDAP directory. This would allow privilege
        escalation within the wider organization or facilitate
        unauthorized access to other information and resources. In
        such a deployment, user provisioning would be out of the realm
        of the OpenStack deployment.</para>
      <note>
        <para>There is an <link
            xlink:href="https://bugs.launchpad.net/ossn/+bug/1168252"
            >OpenStack Security Note (OSSN) regarding keystone.conf
            permissions</link>.</para>
        <para>There is an <link
            xlink:href="https://bugs.launchpad.net/ossn/+bug/1155566"
            >OpenStack Security Note (OSSN) regarding potential DoS
            attacks</link>.</para>
      </note>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="identity-authentication-methods-external-authentication-methods">
      <title>External authentication methods</title>
      <para>Organizations may desire to implement external
        authentication for compatibility with existing authentication
        services or to enforce stronger authentication policy
        requirements. Although passwords are the most common form of
        authentication, they can be compromised through numerous
        methods, including keystroke logging and password compromise.
        External authentication services can provide alternative forms
        of authentication that minimize the risk from weak
        passwords.</para>
      <para>These include:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Password policy enforcement: Requires user passwords
            to conform to minimum standards for length, diversity of
            characters, expiration, or failed login attempts.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Multi-factor authentication: The authentication
            service requires the user to provide information based on
            something they have, such as a one-time password token or
            X.509 certificate, and something they know, such as a
            password.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Kerberos</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

</section>
