<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="introduction-to-case-studies">
  <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
  <title>Introduction to case studies</title>
  <para>This guide refers to two running case studies, which are
    introduced here and referred to at the end of each chapter.</para>
  <section xml:id="introduction-to-case-studies-case-study-alice-the-private-cloud-builder">
    <title>Case study: Alice, the private cloud builder</title>
    <para>Alice is a technical manager overseeing a new OpenStack
      deployment for the US government in support of Healthcare.gov. The
      load on the cloud is expected to be variable, with moderate usage
      increasing to heavy usage during annual enrollment periods. She is
      aware that her private cloud will need to be certified against
      FISMA through the FedRAMP accreditation process required for all
      federal agencies, departments, and contractors as well as being
      under HIPAA purview. These compliance frameworks will place the
      burden of effort around logging, reporting, and policy. While
      technical controls will require Alice to use Public Key
      Infrastructure to encrypt wire-level communication, and SELinux
      for Mandatory Access Controls, Alice will invest in tool
      development to automate the reporting. Additionally, comprehensive
      documentation is expected covering application and network
      architecture, controls, and other details. The FedRAMP
      classification of Alice's system is High per FIPS-199. Alice will
      leverage existing authentication/authorization infrastructure in
      the form of Microsoft Active Directory, and an existing enterprise
      SEIM deployment that she will use to build new views and correlation
      rules to better monitor the state of her cloud.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="introduction-to-case-studies-case-study-bob-the-public-cloud-provider">
    <title>Case study: Bob, the public cloud provider</title>
    <para>Bob is a lead architect for a company that deploys a large
      greenfield public cloud. This cloud provides IaaS for the masses
      and enables any consumer with a valid credit card access to
      utility computing and storage, but the primary focus is
      enterprise customers. Data privacy concerns are a big priority
      for Bob as they are seen as a major barrier to large-scale
      adoption of the cloud by organizations.</para>
  </section>
</section>
